<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An elegy on that faithful and laborious minister of Christ, Mr Francis Bampfield, who died in Newgate on the Sabbath day, vulg. Februar. 16th. 1683/4. Being in the 70th. year of his age.</title>
            <author>J. S.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B05964</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S53</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Interim Tract Supplement Guide C.20.f.3[5]</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99885166</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">ocm99885166</idno>
            <idno type="VID">182491</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B05964)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 182491)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; Tract supplement ; A4:1[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An elegy on that faithful and laborious minister of Christ, Mr Francis Bampfield, who died in Newgate on the Sabbath day, vulg. Februar. 16th. 1683/4. Being in the 70th. year of his age.</title>
                  <author>J. S.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J. Lawrence at the Angel in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Verse: "Wrapt in her mourning weed, my grieved muse ..."</note>
                  <note>At end of text: The second part by J.S.</note>
                  <note>After imprint date: Where Mr. Bampfields works may be had.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bampfield, Francis, 1615 or 16-1683 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Elegiac poetry, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:182491:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <head>AN ELEGY On that Faithful and Laborious Miniſter of Chriſt, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> FRANCIS BAMPFIELD, Who Died in <hi>Newgate</hi> on the Sabbath Day, <date>
                  <hi>vulg. Februar.</hi> 16th. 1683/4.</date> Being in the 70th. Year of His Age. <date>
                  <add>5. March. 1684/5</add>
               </date>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>WRapt in her mourning Weed, my grieved Muſe,</l>
               <l>To tune ſuch heavy Notes, at firſt refus'd;</l>
               <l>Rather deſiring to effund her Tears</l>
               <l>In ſecret, where no man nor ſees, nor hears:</l>
               <l>Till ſecond Thoughts, Thoughts on ſo Worthy a Name,</l>
               <l>With greater Energy and Power came,</l>
               <l>And made her Tears in ſlow-pac'd Numbers fall.</l>
               <l>To Sprinkle the Lugubrious Funeral.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l>Come skilful Mourners with ſad Harmony</l>
                  <l>Embalm a Saints thrice Bleſſed Memory</l>
                  <l>With ſighing Songs and mournful Melody;</l>
               </lg>
               <l>In doleful Lines your preſſing grief make known</l>
               <l>Lines, ſtopt with ſighs, and accented with groans,</l>
               <l>Your watry eyes to ſtreaming Riv'lets turn,</l>
               <l>And bath with pious Tears his ſilent Urn;</l>
               <l>That being impregnate with ſuch Fertile ſhowers,</l>
               <l>It may at length produce ſome fragrant flowers,</l>
               <l>Which may with Nature's Tap'ſtry cloth his Tomb,</l>
               <l>And to all generations yet to come,</l>
               <l>Convey an odoriferous Perfume,</l>
               <l>While Braſs and Marble Monuments conſume.</l>
               <l>Thoſe Lips that Milk and Honey did diſtill,</l>
               <l>And with ſweet Balm our wounded Souls did fill,</l>
               <l>Whence pureſt Eloquence did flow; Behold</l>
               <l>How wan they are, appal'd with ſtupid Cold.</l>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thoſe ſuppliant Palms that Faith did elevate</l>
                  <l>So oft to reach th'Eternal Mercy-Seat;</l>
                  <l>And oft return'd with bounteous Grace repleat,</l>
               </lg>
               <l>Are now of Senſe and Motion quite bereft,</l>
               <l>And nothing but their languid Form is left:</l>
               <l>Thoſe Eyes wherein we ſaw Graces Divine</l>
               <l>With Reverend Gravity ſo lively ſhine,</l>
               <l>That oft did ſteep our Sins with precious Rain,</l>
               <l>Are now with ſable clouds of Death beſtain'd;</l>
               <l>That lovely Countenance, that gracious Face,</l>
               <l>Which Nature with ſweet Lineaments did grace,</l>
               <l>And Grace refin'd; which to Beholders preacht,</l>
               <l>And did with charming aſpects Vertue teach,</l>
               <l>Lo now what ſee we there, but Death alone,</l>
               <l>Sitting in Triumph on his Pallid Throne!</l>
               <l>Help <hi>LORD,</hi> thou haſt impos'd a weighty Croſs;</l>
               <l>Save us, a Faithful Watchman we have loſt:</l>
               <l>A careful Shepherd thou haſt tak'n away;</l>
               <l>Keep thou thy Lambs, or elſe they go aſtray:</l>
               <l>Why doſt withdraw thy precious Stars of Light;</l>
               <l>And lead us in the diſmal Shades of Night?</l>
               <l>Shall we Phyſicians want to cure our Souls?</l>
               <l>Whilſt feſtering Sins wound us without controul;</l>
               <l>And ſhall we pine for want of Living Bread?</l>
               <l>Or ſhall our hungry Souls with Husks be fed?</l>
               <l>O Heav'ns forbid it! Give us not Droſs for Gold;</l>
               <l>Let younger Prophets ſtill ſucceed the Old:</l>
               <l>When Fathers die, let Children ſtill inherit</l>
               <l>Their Fathers Vertues and Paſtoral Spirit,</l>
               <l>When our <hi>Elijah</hi>'s are aſſum'd to Heav'n,</l>
               <l>Let young <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s evermore be giv'n:</l>
               <lg>
                  <l>If thus, O <hi>LORD,</hi> thou cut our Fir-Trees down</l>
                  <l>And lay'ſt our pleaſant Cedars on the ground,</l>
                  <l>Where ſhall a Shelter for the Shrubs be found?</l>
               </lg>
               <l>But ſince we have our Fate ſo long bewail'd,</l>
               <l>Let Sobs be curb'd, and ſerious Thoughts recall'd;</l>
               <l>Whilſt rapt in holy Viſions we deſcry</l>
               <l>The Place where Tears are wip'd from ev'ry Eye,</l>
               <l>With Faith's Perſpective we may ſpie the Shore,</l>
               <l>Whither our Faithful Guide is gone before;</l>
               <l>We may on <hi>Nebo</hi>'s Mount a Proſpect gain,</l>
               <l>To view the ſtately Hills, and goodly Plains</l>
               <lg>
                  <l>Of the Celeſtial <hi>Canaan;</hi> there we ſee</l>
                  <l>In Bleſſed Manſions Saints and Martyrs free</l>
                  <l>From ſervile Chains, keeping their Jubilee.</l>
               </lg>
               <l>Lo! Chriſt his Servants home begins to call</l>
               <l>In Anger, maugre all the Bars and Walls;</l>
               <l>As if his Glorious Majeſty diſdain'd</l>
               <l>That Mortals ſhould his Meſſengers enchain.</l>
               <l>Sleep then (Dear Saint) in Peace and ſoftly Reſt.</l>
               <l>Till Chriſt reſuſcitate thy Quiet Duſt,</l>
               <l>To cloath it with immortal Beams of Light;</l>
               <l>That with its Bright'ned Soul it may unite:</l>
               <l>Mean while thy Soul doth learn to tune the Lays</l>
               <l>Which Angels utter in their Hymns of Praiſe.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <head>An EPITAPH.</head>
            <l>Whilſt I in Pilgrimage did Sojourn here,</l>
            <l>Reproach and Captive Bonds did ſtill attend me;</l>
            <l>I ſpent in Priſon more than twice five years,</l>
            <l>A full ſev'nth part of th' time my God did lend me:</l>
            <l>But now being free of th' <hi>New Jeruſalem,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>I've chang'd my Priſon for a Diadem.</l>
            <byline>The Second Part By J. S.</byline>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>J. Lawrence</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1684 Where Mr. <hi>Bampfields</hi> Works may be had.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
